<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Civil War on LoCoHistory</title>
    <link>http://www.locohistory.org/categories/civil-war/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Civil War on LoCoHistory</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 May 2012 13:05:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.locohistory.org/categories/civil-war/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrate C-ville&#39;s 250th Anniversary</title>
      <link>http://www.locohistory.org/blog/albemarle/2012/05/23/celebrate-c-villes-250th-anniversary/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2012 13:05:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.locohistory.org/blog/albemarle/2012/05/23/celebrate-c-villes-250th-anniversary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This year marks the 250th anniversary of the founding of Charlottesville (1762). There will be activities all year, but the focus of the celebrations is a one-week tour-de-force of Charlottesville&amp;rsquo;s rich and diverse history. The festivities begin on May 26th (see below) and continue through June 3. The following list highlights the theme for each day:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 26 - Remembering Those Who Died in the Civil War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 27 - Remembering the 200th Anniversary in 1962&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 28 - 250 Years of Sacrifice in Our Nation&amp;rsquo;s Wars&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 29 - 250 Years of African-American Community Life&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 30 - 250 Years of Growing Neighborhoods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 31 - 250 Years of Religion, Education and Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;June 1 - 250 Years of Architecture, Development and Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;June 2 - Living History Festival of Our First 200 Years&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;June 3 - Reenactment of the British invasion of 1781&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a summary of the events for the &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; week (click on the image for a larger picture). But please visit the official &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.celebrate250.com&#34;&gt;Celebrate 250 website&lt;/a&gt; for complete information and the location of each event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.locohistory.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/05/250_events2012.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hungrytown (Part II)</title>
      <link>http://www.locohistory.org/blog/albemarle/2009/09/13/hungrytown-part-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2009 21:13:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.locohistory.org/blog/albemarle/2009/09/13/hungrytown-part-ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two years ago I published a post about Hungrytown, in southern Albemarle County.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.locohistory.org/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/hungrytownhouse.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;An historic cabin in Hungrytown&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I received an email from a descendant asking about a nearby cemetery. I visited the cemetery a number of years ago. It contains the graves of families who lived in the neighborhood: Toms, Meltons, and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.locohistory.org/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/hungrytowncem4-128x150.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately only one stone is inscribed: that of a veteran, Wilton Toms (1828-1910) who served in the 46th Virginia Infantry during the Civil War. The stone was placed recently, in the past decade or so, to commemorate his service. The other family members are buried under fieldstones, some shaped, others plain. The fate of this cemetery - unmarked stones in a hard-to-find, rural location - is all too common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.locohistory.org/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/hungrytowncem3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where rural communities once flourished and shared the knowledge of who was buried in which grave, today these neighborhoods are often unpopulated or the original residents (and their memories) are long gone. One option for preserving the location of historic burials is to install a metal plaque with a list of the names of the dead. This information could be collected from the memory of residents and family members. While it would not be possible, in most cases, to assign names to individual graves, a plaque would help preserve the family ties to the graveyard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.locohistory.org/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/hungrytowncem1-150x150.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another option is submitting a list of burials and photographs to a nearby historical society and/or county planning department. That way there will be a paper trail for future researchers. Perhaps the most important strategy for protecting these sites is to keep the memory of the dead alive in the younger generations so that they feel connected to these sacred spaces, visit, and care for the graves. This is easier said than done, but making the effort will ensure that these historic burial grounds are not forgotten by the next generation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>