<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Revolutionary War on LoCoHistory</title>
    <link>http://www.locohistory.org/categories/revolutionary-war/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Revolutionary War on LoCoHistory</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 May 2012 13:05:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.locohistory.org/categories/revolutionary-war/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrate C-ville&#39;s 250th Anniversary</title>
      <link>http://www.locohistory.org/blog/albemarle/2012/05/23/celebrate-c-villes-250th-anniversary/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2012 13:05:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.locohistory.org/blog/albemarle/2012/05/23/celebrate-c-villes-250th-anniversary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This year marks the 250th anniversary of the founding of Charlottesville (1762). There will be activities all year, but the focus of the celebrations is a one-week tour-de-force of Charlottesville&amp;rsquo;s rich and diverse history. The festivities begin on May 26th (see below) and continue through June 3. The following list highlights the theme for each day:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 26 - Remembering Those Who Died in the Civil War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 27 - Remembering the 200th Anniversary in 1962&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 28 - 250 Years of Sacrifice in Our Nation&amp;rsquo;s Wars&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 29 - 250 Years of African-American Community Life&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 30 - 250 Years of Growing Neighborhoods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 31 - 250 Years of Religion, Education and Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;June 1 - 250 Years of Architecture, Development and Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;June 2 - Living History Festival of Our First 200 Years&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;June 3 - Reenactment of the British invasion of 1781&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a summary of the events for the &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; week (click on the image for a larger picture). But please visit the official &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.celebrate250.com&#34;&gt;Celebrate 250 website&lt;/a&gt; for complete information and the location of each event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.locohistory.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/05/250_events2012.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lions, Tigers, Hessians, Oh My!</title>
      <link>http://www.locohistory.org/blog/albemarle/2007/04/02/lions-tigers-hessians-oh-my/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2007 03:17:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.locohistory.org/blog/albemarle/2007/04/02/lions-tigers-hessians-oh-my/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the Revolutionary War, the Barracks (located west of the shopping center; today a horse stable) was a prison for British and German troops captured at The Battle of Saratoga in October 1777. &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.locohistory.org/wp-content/uploads/2007/03/hessian.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A German Hessian Soldier&#34; /&gt;They were originally imprisoned by Revolutionary forces in Massachusetts, but within the year they marched 628 miles to the more hospitable climate of Charlottesville, Virginia. The term &amp;ldquo;hessian&amp;rdquo; is a reference to the German mercenaries who fought for the British. Hence, the nearby housing development on Georgetown Road called &amp;ldquo;Hessian Hills.&amp;rdquo; Although no prisoner list survives, estimates suggest over 4,000 prisoners lived at the Barracks. By the spring of 1779, locals described the camp as a small town with a commissary store, a coffeehouse, and a theater. Despite these amenities, over 1,000 prisoners escaped between 1779 and 1780. Many of the German soldiers settled in the Shenandoah Valley and became American citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Barracks Road Shopping Center</title>
      <link>http://www.locohistory.org/blog/albemarle/2007/03/14/barracks-road-shopping-center/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2007 20:29:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.locohistory.org/blog/albemarle/2007/03/14/barracks-road-shopping-center/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.barracksroad.com/ourcommunity.php&#34;&gt;Barracks Road Shopping Center&lt;/a&gt; is one of the oldest in the country, dating to 1959. To view the rest of this great old photograph of Barracks Road, see Cville Dave&amp;rsquo;s Posting on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cvilledave.blogspot.com/2007/01/barracks-road-shopping-center-early.html&#34;&gt;Barracks Road Shopping Center in the 1960s.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.locohistory.org/wp-content/uploads/2007/03/barracks1960s.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Barracks Road, circa 1960s&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the photo you can see the newly built shopping center, mostly surrounded by woods, with large expanses of asphalt for the &amp;ldquo;acres of free parking&amp;rdquo; that was touted in the original advertisement. Built by an area developer, Rinehart, it displaced a famous tavern called Carroll&amp;rsquo;s Tea Room. Moore&amp;rsquo;s history of Charlottesville reports that although it often possessed neither tea nor room, it was &amp;ldquo;an oasis for thousands of thirsty university students.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.locohistory.org/wp-content/uploads/2007/03/barrackslogo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Barracks Road Logo&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look closely at the Barracks Road logo, found on signs along the edges of the retail center, you will notice a rider on a horse. This logo references the cavalry soldiers who manned the &amp;ldquo;Barracks.&amp;rdquo; The military barracks were constructed west of town near Ivy Farms during the Revolutionary War to house British and German prisoners-of-war.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>