<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Origins on LoCoHistory</title>
    <link>http://www.locohistory.org/categories/origins/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Origins on LoCoHistory</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2008 20:37:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.locohistory.org/categories/origins/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Sir Jeffrey</title>
      <link>http://www.locohistory.org/blog/amherst/2008/06/04/sir-jeffrey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2008 20:37:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.locohistory.org/blog/amherst/2008/06/04/sir-jeffrey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The area now called &amp;ldquo;Amherst County&amp;rdquo; was Monacan land for 1000s of years before the first Europeans arrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.locohistory.org/wp-content/uploads/2008/06/sirjamherst.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sir Jeffrey Amherst, painted by Joshua Reynolds in 1765.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the Europeans arrived on the scene they had a tendency to name every feature and land mass in sight. In the case of the county, it was named after Sir Jeffrey Amherst (1717-1797), a British Baron who was eventually promoted to Field Marshal after his service in the Seven Years&amp;rsquo; War. The North American campaign, called the French and Indian Wars (1754-63), pitted the British against French forces and their Native American allies. Amherst fought most of these battles on Canadian soil, leading to the moniker &amp;ldquo;Conquerer of Canada.&amp;rdquo; While Amherst achieved many victories, he did so at a great cost. In a letter dated 16 July 1763 then General Amherst approved a suggestion to distribute blankets to &amp;ldquo;inoculate the Indians&amp;rdquo; with smallpox from gifts of contaminated blankets (the idea was suggested by Gen Bouquet in a letter dated 13 July 1763). Gen Amherst went further and suggested that he &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip; try Every other method that can serve to Extirpate this Execrable Race&amp;rdquo; (Source &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.umass.edu/legal/derrico/&#34;&gt;Peter d&amp;rsquo;Errico&lt;/a&gt; and the website link is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nativeweb.org/pages/legal/amherst/lord_jeff.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The county of Amherst was formed in 1761 when it was separated from Albemarle County.  In 1806, Nelson County was created, leaving Amherst with its modern-day boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>