<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mills on LoCoHistory</title>
    <link>http://www.locohistory.org/categories/mills/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mills on LoCoHistory</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2008 00:19:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.locohistory.org/categories/mills/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Sandidges Mill</title>
      <link>http://www.locohistory.org/blog/amherst/2008/07/10/sandidges-mill/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2008 00:19:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.locohistory.org/blog/amherst/2008/07/10/sandidges-mill/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.locohistory.org/wp-content/uploads/2008/07/sandidge1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sandidges Mill (photo by Kelly Murphy and Jami Kontkanen)&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amherst County contains 100s of historic structures. Many of these buildings point to a by-gone lifestyle.  A perfect example is a mill. Once a necessity (for sawing lumber or processing grains), these businesses (and ruins thereof) were usually surrounded by a small community because it became an important location for trade, exchange, and the processing of goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s historic feature is the 1810s [corrected date, see comment below] Sandidges Mill, located in the eponymous town (west of Amherst, off Route 60). This small community once had a church, post office, and store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.locohistory.org/wp-content/uploads/2008/07/sandidge3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;An Old Advertisement for their Services (photo by Kelly Murphy and Jami Kontkanen)&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today the building lies in ruins, but you can still read the advertisement for &amp;ldquo;feed&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;flour&amp;rdquo; if you look carefully. They ground corn and flour for local farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The photo below shows a mill race that once brought water to power the mill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.locohistory.org/wp-content/uploads/2008/07/sandidge2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Mill Race at Sandidges’ Mill (photo by Kelly Murphy and Jami Kontkanen)&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mill closed in 1942 and the usable equipment was taken to Brightwell&amp;rsquo;s Mill. If you visit the &lt;a href=&#34;http://members.aol.com/achmuseum/muse/museoct05.html&#34;&gt;Amherst County Museum &amp;amp; Historical Society&lt;/a&gt; you can view an old pamphlet that illustrates milling equipment from Sandidges Mill.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hartman&#39;s Milling Company</title>
      <link>http://www.locohistory.org/blog/albemarle/2008/01/01/hartmans-milling-company/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2008 03:19:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.locohistory.org/blog/albemarle/2008/01/01/hartmans-milling-company/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.locohistory.org/wp-content/uploads/2007/12/hartmansmill.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;1907 Sanborn Map&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is a plea for information - to see if anyone knows historic details about the Albemarle Roller Mill (used by the Hartman Mill), located on a tributary of Moore&amp;rsquo;s Creek.  The mill was used to process either lumber  or flour. Today the site is located somewhere near Hartman&amp;rsquo;s Mill Road (between Ridge and Avon St). The drawing at the right comes from the 1907 Sanborn Fire Insurance Map and the complete image includes about half-a-dozen associated outbuilding. The Scottsville Road indicated on the map is probably located near today&amp;rsquo;s Avon Street which once connected to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.locohistory.org/wp-content/uploads/2007/12/hartman1875.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Peyton Map 1875&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1875 Peyton map illustrates Hartman&amp;rsquo;s Mill at a horseshoe bend in Moore&amp;rsquo;s Creek, one mile southwest of the courthouse. Old mills needed a source of power - the mill race, powered by gravity. Hartman&amp;rsquo;s Mill ran at 100 revolutions per minute, using water from a tributary of Moore&amp;rsquo;s Creek. The &amp;ldquo;head race&amp;rdquo; (labelled here &amp;ldquo;Mill Race&amp;rdquo;) carried water from the dam to the mill site. The water wheel (at the mill) produced electricity. The &amp;ldquo;tail race&amp;rdquo; returned the water to the stream. The site would have also included millstones (circular features that were used to grind flours). Most mills also included the home of the miller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If anyone knows the location of the mill or has any additional historic documentation about it, please post a comment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>